Finding Aid for Nancy A. Walker Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Nancy A. Walker Papers
2016
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0837
1.26 linear feet
Nancy A. Walker Biography
Born in 1942, Walker grew up in Shreveport, Louisiana. A budding academic in high school with a passion for literature—as expressed in her letters—she matriculated at Louisiana State University, where she continued to study English. After studying abroad in London, Walker earned her Ph.D. in American Literature at Kent State in 1971. She taught English at Stephens College in Columbia, Missouri for several years before accepting a position as an associate professor of English at Vanderbilt University and as the director of the burgeoning Women's Studies Committee in 1989.
Upon arriving at Vanderbilt Walker expanded the Women's Studies Committee into a full-fledged undergraduate academic program eligible as a minor in the School of Arts & Sciences. Over the course of her career, Walker published several acclaimed works on the role of women, humor, and pop culture, in American Society. Her most notable include A Very Serious Thing: Women's Humor and American Culture and Women's Magazines, 1940-1960: Gender Roles and the Popular Press. She also edited countless works of women's literature from Kate Chopin to Eudora Welty.
In her personal life—largely disclosed in the correspondence—Walker kept close touch with the recipient of these letters, Charles "Jeff" Howie throughout her life. Walker married her first husband, John Hand, in the late 1960s. They divorced in 1974. Not long after, Walker married Bert Augst. Walker's correspondence with Howie reveals her difficult, but supportive, long-distance relationship with Augst in the early years of their marriage as he worked in Alaska.
Walker continued to teach as a professor of English and the director of the Women's Studies Program until she passed in December 2000.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is comprised of letters exchanged between Nancy A. Walker, the late Vanderbilt English Professor and the Director of the Women's Studies Center, and her childhood friend, Charles "Jeff" Howie date from 1959 to 1995. The vast majority of letters were exchanged during the 1960s as Walker studied English at Louisiana State University and completed her Ph.D. at Kent State. The collection solely comprises of her outgoing mail.
The letters are deeply personal and colloquial in nature. The earliest correspondence during Walker's time as a high school student in Shreveport reveals her growing enchantment with literature as well as her concerns about gossip, high school dances, college, and sororities. As an undergraduate at LSU, Walker keeps close touch with Howie, who studied law close-by at Tulane at this time. She discusses her studies and sorority activities in depth. She also elaborates on her readings and recommends several books. Walker sends several letters from London during her time abroad in the fall of 1965. She enters a relationship with her first husband, Jack Hand, around 1966 and correspondence falters until 1967 when she reopens conversation with Howie about her Ph.D. program and—rather candidly—her doubts about her marriage with Hand. Walker keeps close contact with Howie as she graduates from Kent State and begins her professorship at Stephens College in the early 1970s.
Contact becomes intermittent as her relationship with Hand falters, resulting in their divorce in 1974. Although Walker's letters become few and far between following this time, they remain incredibly frank. Her letters in the late 1970s reveal the difficult longdistance relationship with her second husband, Bert Augst. Walker terms this as a "midlife" crisis, highlighted by an affair with a "friend/lover" in Columbus, Missouri while Augst works in Alaska. Walker and Howie's correspondence slows to annual holiday letters between 1987 and 1995. During this time, she reveals her excitement upon accepting a position at Vanderbilt, and also her satisfaction with the growth of the Women's Studies Program in 1990.
The collection, as a whole, unveils Walker's maturation as an English professor and her focus on Women's Right, contrasted with her experience as a professional female from the 1960s to 1980s.
- 1959-June 1961 (14 folders)
  - 1959 (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - January 1960 (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - February 1960 (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - March 1960 (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - April 1960 (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - May 1-May 21, 1960 (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - May 23-June 1960 (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - July 1960 (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - August 1960 (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - September 1960 (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - October-December 1960 (Folder 11, Box 1)
  - February-March 1961 (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - April-May 1960 (Folder 13, Box 1)
  - June 1961 (Folder 14, Box 1)
- July 1961-November 1965 (15 Folders)
  - July 1961 (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - August-September 1961 (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - October-December 1961 (Folder 3, Box 2)
  - January-February 1961 (Folder 4, Box 2)
  - March-May 1962 (Folder 5, Box 2)
  - September-December 1962 (Folder 6, Box 2)
  - 1963 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - January-April 1964 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - May-June 1964 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - July-August 1964 (Folder 10, Box 2)
  - February-June 7, 1965 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - June 9-June 30, 1965 (Folder 12, Box 2)
  - July 1965 (Folder 13, Box 2)
  - August-October 14, 1965 (Folder 14, Box 2)
  - October 20-November 21, 1965 (Folder 15, Box 2)
- May 1967-1995 (15 Folders)
  - May-December 1967 (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - May-December 1968 (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - January-June 1969 (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - July-October 1969 (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - 1970 (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - March 1971-March 1972 (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - 1973 (Folder 7, Box 3)
  - January-July 1974 (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - August-December 1974 (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - January-August 1975 (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - March-September 1975 (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - 1978-1986 (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - 1987 (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - 1988-1991 (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - 1992-1995 (Folder 15, Box 3)